翻译，时间轴，压制: Bolshevik0
下划线原文为我没听清的部分
Everybody run.
大家快跑
It's coming. It's coming.
它来了
We're being attacked by Bad CG.
我们被差CG攻击了
In the past anime and CG have not had the best public relationship.
在过去 动画和CG的关系并没有现在这么好
The general reaction from someone
对某人而言
when they hear the mere mention of CG being integrated into their favorite anime
当他们听说自己最爱的动漫中有CG的制作
is that they pack up and start running a fucking mile
他们肯定会对此非常嫌弃
注: 翻译成辣脆是自我规制
like they've just found out we're getting invaded by Nazis.
就像被辣脆入侵一样
Or even more horrifyingly,  CG Nazis.
或者更恐怖的东西 CG辣脆
But today I wanted to evaluate
但是今天我想评估一下
if CG really deserves its reputation within the anime community.
CG技术是否在动漫社群中获得了应有的名声
What are some examples of it being used well and badly
哪些是CG技术运用的优秀例子或者失败例子
and what are some of the different ways that CG have been integrated into anime.
还有就是动漫中的CG技术又是以哪些方式被运用的
So first we need to answer the question what is Bad CG?
首先我们需要定义差CG
And here's the catch.
举个例
You aren't allowed to use any word that rhymes with Sheshmerk 2017.
你不可以用任何和Sheshmerk 2017押韵的词汇
Well if we look at the dictionary definition of Bad CG,
如果我们仔细阅读差CG的词典定义
we can quite clearly see that,
我们就很清楚
all for fuck's sake,
都是些辣鸡
I'm sure we can all agree that
有一点可以达成共识
注: CGI = Computer-generated imagery，即计算机产生图像
a CGI face that is noticeable enough to take you out of your immersion
那就是一张CGI的脸足够让你失去看番的沉浸感
and break your suspension of disbelief
中止你对这个世界的幻想
and out of place objects, some stupid looking expression.
包括一些不能突兀的物体 一些崩坏的表情
A lot of things can take you out of an exprience.
许多东西都会影响你的观看体验
But that's the thing to keep in mind.
有一件事你需要知道
Bad CG is Bad CG
差CG就是差CG
because you notice Bad CG.
因为你注意到了差CG
Bad CG. Sorry I just wanted to say Bad CG one more time.
差CG 对不起我只是想再说一遍差CG这个词
I think a good place to start
如何展开这个话题
is just seeing how the general use and look of CG has evolved over time.
首先是要看看CG技术是如何逐渐地被广泛地应用与观看
We normally associate CG with more modern age anime.
一般而言 我们更多地把CG技术与现代动画联系起来
The have been around for a lot longer than people think
不过CG技术的出现远比人们想象中的早
and over time has gotten better blending in objects.
而且逐渐更加擅长用于物体的渲染
If you look at most mordern anime carefully,
如果你仔细地观看各种现代动画
you'd be hard-pressed to find one that
你很难找到
doesn't incorporate some sort of computer rendered object in it
那些不使用CG技术渲染物体的动画
and a lot of the time you don't notice because it's not something that significant.
更多的情况下你甚至都注意不到这个问题 因为这无关紧要
There's been a lot of debate over
人们总在争论
how CG has changed a lot of the general look of mechs over the years
CG技术这些年来是如何大幅改变机甲动画的
and honestly I think it comes down to how bland and forgettable modern mechs feel.
实话说这就涉及到了现代机甲动画是有多么平淡乏味
They all move the same.
他们动作一致
They all feel the same.
观感一致
注: video game就是电子游戏，别再说什么电视游戏
With the same clunky video game style that
都像是笨重的电子游戏风格
never looks quite as natural as hand-drawn mechs.
永远也没有手绘机甲那样地自然
Nothing becomes as memorable
再也没有以前那样令人难忘
even if you have a cool design.
即使你的机设很帅
I mean fuck,
我是指
Chamber from Suisei no Gargantia
翠星的伽鲁冈缇亚 的机甲Chamber 的大小
had the size of seasoned Las Vegas poor dancer.
就和拉斯维加斯经验丰富的舞者的房间一样大
and this was never appreciating to them enough.
而这么说还是夸奖了他们
Damn……
可恶……
That is a dickass ball.
贼鸡儿恐怖
Whether it be to speed up the production time
不管是为了加速生产时间
or make up for a lack of talents who can animate mechs well
或者是为了弥补无法设计出好机甲的不足才能
it feels like CG makes a use as a compensation tool rather than a deliberate creative decision
就像是CG技术是用来随意填补漏洞的手段而非故意使用的创意工具
because when done correctly, they look just as fantastic.
因为CG技术运用得当的话并不会比传统机甲动画差到哪里去
The sequences of the Unicorn transforming look fucking amazing.
高达UC那段变形看着着实过瘾
and the reason they do this is because they're done in CG.
而正因为使用了CG技术才能做到如此优秀
Trying to animate this level of complicated mechanical panel movement
想要制做这样复杂的机械运动动画
would be absurdly difficult by hand
几乎不可能用纯手绘的方法办到
and they managed to make it not look like an in-engine video game cut scene.
而他们设法做到了让这一切看起来不像是电子游戏的剧情动画
However one thing that the industry is still figuring out how to do correctly
然而 有一件事业界还在探索当中
is with characters.
那就是人物的CG渲染
And it doesn't matter if they are in the foreground or the background.
不管是前景人物还是背景人物
There's an old Chinese proverb that goes
有个中国古代谚语说
条条大路通罗马
注: 不太清楚原句是什么，套一个类似的翻译吧
unless that crosswalk contains a CG anime crowd
但是不适用于充满了CG渲染人群的路口
in which case you're probably burning in hell.
这种情况下你可能会被烧死在地狱
Yeah CGI crowds are the one thing I think are destined to always look like complete shit.
没错 我始终认为CG渲染的人群不论在任何情况下都像一坨屎
Nothing's more distracting than when there's something important going on
当剧情进展到关键时刻
but your brain unable to focus on anything
没什么比这更让人分心
but the same 5 PlayStation 2 motherfuckers hangout in the background
就是你大脑只能关注着背景里5个PS2画质的路人而无法关注在剧情上
trying have horrendously bad to blend in.
糟糕得完全不能融入
Why me!
为什么是我
Why does your face look like Bad CG?
为什么你的脸看上去像差CG
Why does everyone look like Bad CG?
为什么每个人都像差CG
My mind is Bad CG nightmare right now.
我的大脑现在也充满着差CG噩梦了
And I really did try finding a good example of anime CGI crowds.
我确实尝试找过CG渲染人群的优秀例子
So if anyone does have any good examples
所以如果有人能找到CG渲染人群的优秀例子
then please contact me at
请按照以下邮箱联系我
注: 邮箱地址意思是 那种不会让我瞎眼的CG渲染人群@gmail.com
But this extends the foreground characters
但是对于前景角色而言也是如此
注: 参见en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncanny_valley，以下节选自中文维基
森政弘的假设指出，由于机器人与人类在外表、动作上相似，所以人类亦会对机器人产生正面的情感。直到一个特定程度，
他们的反应便会突然变得极为负面。可是，当机器人和人类的相似度继续上升，相当于普通人之间的相似度的时候，
人类对他们的情感反应会再度回到正面，产生人类与人类之间的移情作用。
恐怖谷 一词用以形容人类对跟他们相似到特定程度之机器人的排斥反应。
where you have to battle against this weird Uncanny Valley effect
你需要对抗奇怪的恐怖谷 理论
where characters kind of like anime but not anime enough.
角色看起来像动画但还不够动画
So when they're just there front and center with no attempt to blend it in.
当他们处在中间或者前面的位置但完全无法融入环境的时候
Your brain has time to process what you're watching so you kind of notice.
你的大脑需要时间处理 某种程度上你会注意到
Wait a minute.
等一下
These are the same guys they hired to do the Mass Effect: Andromeda facial animation.
这些人应该也做质量效应: 仙女座 的表情动画
Even when they look competent.
即使看起来能胜任
When you are restricted to 3D models emulating a 2D-R-style,
当你被限制用3D模型模仿2D渲染风格的时候
there is less freedom to work with when it comes to subtle expressions.
处理那些细微的表情变化就变得更加困难
Nuanced character animation.
角色的细节动画
And even the best examples we've had so far,
即使是我们现在能举出的最佳例子
don't even come close to the best examples in 2D animation yet.
和2D动画中的最好的例子比起来 也难以望其项背
Things are looking better
不过事情正在向好的方向发展
but the next problem is actually being able to blend these two elements.
不过下一个问题是如何从实际角度出发让这两种元素融合在一起
The issue you face when you blend 2D animation with 3D elements
在2D动画中融入3D元素
is the aesthetic clash.
你面临的问题是美学意义上的冲突
When we are watching an animated show,
我们看动画的时候
we know it is an animated show that does not exist within our universe.
我们知道这是现实中不存在的东西
But we are fully invested in suspending our disbelief for that world.
但是我们又投入大量精力去相信那个世界的存在
However, if you see two objects that blatantly look like they don't belong in the same universe,
但是 如果你看到两个物体显然不属于同一个世界的时候
it was against that suspension of disbelief.
就会抵触你对这个世界的信任感
Golden Kamuy is the latest example of this,
黄金神威 是这方面最新的例子
where you have a standard anime characters fighting that
在这个动画里面
fucking bear from Far Cry 5 with a cel-shaded wolf in a background of green screen fire effects.
2D的角色和孤岛惊魂5 里卡通渲染版本的狼在绿幕火焰效果的背景中作战
The visual cohesion is an absolute mess
视觉效果一团糟
and personally I much prefer this early leaked test footage.
就我个人而言 我更喜欢这段早期泄漏版本的测试短片
At least it has a uniform visual style which you know just makes the fights
至少它有个统一的视觉风格
It's just far more believable.
让这场战斗更可信
Oh no, an angel.
看 那有天使
Different aesthetics only really work
不同的美学元素混搭仅在以下几种情况起正面作用
when the juxtaposition is purposefully part of the visual style
这种混搭本身就是视觉风格的重要组成部分
or when it's supposed to happen narratively.
或者是作用于叙事
There are, however, effective ways to blend the two elements that we are seeing more often.
当然也有更常见的 更加有效的方法让这两者融合在一起
When CG is limited to dynamic background environments,
当CG技术的运用仅限于动态背景的环境当中
the fast-paced movement of the foreground animation is only enhanced
这增强了前景动画的高速运动
allowing for more freedom of camera movements
允许摄像机更自由地移动
which results in being able to complex shot like this
这将允许更复杂的镜头譬如这样
without giving the viewer adequate time to notice the aesthetic clash.
而不给观众足够的时间发觉这种冲突
There are countless examples from Attack on Titan to Code Geass: Akito the Exiled,
在动画自由之翼 或者Code Geass 亡国的阿基德 中 这样的例子太多了
even some of the more intricate shot from Monogatari which fully take advantage of this
甚至在物语系列 中一些更加复杂的镜头 也是充分利用到了这一点
or with other shows that had some shots that were rotoscoped with the aid of CG tools.
至于有些动画则是有些镜头借助了CG技术转描成2D部分
The important thing is that the CG is never the main focus.
重要的是 CG技术永远不是主角
Always rendered in such a way that it naturally fits in with the visual style of the show.
CG技术总是按照融入动画视觉风格的方式来渲染
In this sense, Ufotable are the fucking gods at this.
在这方面来讲 Ufotable 简直高到不知道哪里去了
Throughout the years they have perfected the art of the digital composition
这些年来他们完善了数字构图的作画方式
and blending traditional animation with computer-aided effects
让传统动画以电脑辅助效果的方式渲染
to the point where you can hardly tell the difference.
达到了一种你无法分清二者的程度
注: 这里指的应该是Fate/Zero(2011)
My first exposure to them was their first take on the Fate franchise.
我对此的第一次体验是他们参与制作的第一个Fate 系列
And then no no not you get the fuck out of here.
当然不是你这个菲特/今晚留下来(2006)
Another time they blew me away and I thought anime couldn't look better than this.
他们又一次震撼到我了 我以为这就是动画的极致
But then they came back with Unlimited Blade Works
之后他们又推出了Fate/stay night [Unlimited Blade Works]
No, not, fucking you.
不 不是你菲特/今晚留下来 [无限刀片工作] 剧场版(2010)
They have continually improved and you and pushed the boundaries so much
他们还在持续改进
so that they have crafted a unique visual style which is instantly recognizable
达到了一种独特可辨识的视觉风格的程度
and no one really calls this CG anime
而没有人称这个动画是CG动画
despite how much they use it.
尽管这个动画使用了非常多的CG技术
But moving on a different problem from blending 2D and 3D
继续探讨一个关于渲染2D和3D的不同的问题
when you are completely switching between the two
当你完全切换两者的时候
Let me set the scene.
让我来假设一种情况
You're enjoying a classic show.
你正在观看一个传统2D动画
It looks awesome.
看起来好极了
The characters look great and we're just about to get to the heart pumping action scene.
角色看起来都很棒 很快就要进入到精彩的动作场景了
Then without any warning it cuts to the action
而在没有任何预警的情况下
and you noticed something's a bit off about way the show looks.
动画就切换到了一种你能察觉出的完全不同的风格
And then just as you get used to it,
正当你习惯了这种风格的时候
it switches back before.
它又切换到之前的样子
And you like, "Okay, maybe my eyes are being funny".
你会感觉到 好吧 我的眼睛瞎了
Then you begin to look really closely and slowly.
接下来你会很仔细很缓慢地观看着
You realize that maybe there is something different about the way the show looks.
你会察觉到也许这个动画就是看起来有些不同
Constantly switching from 2D to 3D to 2D again
经常在2D和3D之间切换
is a guaranteed method to make the viewer feel a sense of visual whiplash.
绝对会让观众感到视觉疲劳
And this semi is right up there with CG crowds for anime things
而这正如CG渲染人群一样的动画
that fucking keep me up at night.
是让我晚上睡不着觉的噩梦原因之一
The most recent offenders I can think of
最近的几个类似的糟糕动画
are with Inuyashiki and the Berserk movie trilogy
是犬屋敷 和剑风传奇 电影三部曲
and the thing is the CG sometimes doesn't even look bad.
我想表达的是 有时CG本身看着没什么问题
I wouldn't even mind if some of these shows were fully 3D.
我甚至不在意这些动画是全3D的
It's just a note don't shut shut the fuck up...
只是提一下 你别说了
Just the constant switching between visual styles
不过是反复切换视觉风格
that break any kind of immerging you could be having.
就会摧毁你之前看动画的各种沉浸感
And I would prefer it so much if they just chose one style and committed to it.
我非常希望他们只选择一种风格 并忠于一种风格
注: 参见en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jazz_hands
I mean we've all heard of Jazz hands.
我的意思是我们都听说过Jazz hands
But have you tried the hottest trend?
但是你尝试过最新的潮流吗
Bad CG piano man?
譬如差CG钢琴演奏
What people don't normally talk about
人们经常不会讨论
however is that the switch can be done well
就是这种切换其实可以做得很好
if we stick to some of the same rules we talked about.
如果遵循以下几个规则
KILL la KILL was a good example.
斩服少女 就是一个正面例子
If I tell you KILL la KILL used a lot CG
如果我说斩服少女 用到了很多CG技术
your mind will probably go back to that
你可能会回想起
one time Satsuki was apparently ice-skating vertically up a building which
有一次鬼龙院皐月垂直滑上一个建筑
How can I adequately put this?
还有比这更合适的吗
But what you probably don't know
但你可能不知道的是
is just how many cuts were completely CG like this shot
类似这个镜头里 非常多的剪辑都是完全由CG技术制作的
or this shot
或者这个镜头
or this entire sequence
亦或是这个片段
where they built an entirely new 3D model
他们制作了完整的全新的3D模型
just to accentuates these few frames
仅仅是为了做这么少数几张画面
and unless you were flicking through frame by frame and know exactly what to look for
除非你一帧一帧地仔细观看
you won't even notice exactly because it was the sky so well.
你甚至不会察觉到 因为背景做得实在太好了
As opposed to being loaded front and center.
而不是放在前景或者中心的位置
But that leads into the Big Daddy.
但是这就讲到了最关键的部分
全3D动画
If there was a final boss for the anime industry,
动画产业遇到的最大的问题
this would be it
会是这个
and for most of the time so far
多数情况下
anime has handled it about as well as
动画处理它就如同
吐槽: 差点看成默克尔
a Facebook surfing candy crush addicted grandma attempting no hits run on Dark Souls.
一个平时就刷刷脸书沉迷消消乐的老奶奶尝试无伤通关黑魂
The problem with a lot of us had with early CG anime
我们遇到的许多早期CG动画的问题
was that they seemingly came in with the approach of trying to emulate the 2D art style
就是他们想要找一种尝试模仿2D艺术风格的方法
with a completely different tool.
而使用完全不同的工具
And it doesn't take a genius to tell you that
很显然的是
if you aren't using your tools correctly it probably won't go well.
工欲善其事必先利其器
Movement felt restricted and robotic.
动作僵化
Characters just weren't as expressive.
角色僵化
注: 这里翻译成张数的原因参见www.zhihu.com/question/46419048
The frame rate sometimes looks really dodgy as they purposely restricted it.
因为刻意的限制 张数看起来很难受
注: 这里指的应该是RWBY的创作者"Monty" Oum，下方字幕意为默哀"Monty" Oum
Something even one guy who helped make silly Internet videos
就算是那种做傻x互联网视频的人
figured out was a dumb fuck idea before an entire industry did.
都在整个业界之前了解到这是个愚蠢的主意
They didn't play to their strengths.
他们没有充分利用CG的优势
But despite this, as time went on, things began improving.
不管这件事 随着时间的流逝 事情也在变得越来越好
Acceptable shows started appearing.
令人可以接受的CG动画开始出现
We slowly started to accept that.
作为观众的我们也逐渐开始接受这类动画
Maybe there could be a space for CG anime.
也许CG动画能存活下来
And just as we thought things were starting to look up,
而正如我们觉着事情正在往好的方向发展的时候
Berserk (2016) came crashed landing into the scene.
剑风传奇(2016) 灾难性地出现了
Oh, fuck.
哎我去
But it's okay.
不过还好
Thanks to the collective effort of every half piece of CG anime come out,
感谢半吊子CG动画的集体出现
we managed to stop this from ruining everything.
我们成功阻止了这部作品(而让这些作品)毁灭了CG动画的全部
Quick, Polygon Pictures release something half decent and maybe we can get out of it.
快点 Polygon Pictures 发布了某些半成品动画 也许我们能逃离这里
Kemono Friends, Nobunaga Concerto, Kado.
动物朋友 信长协奏曲 正确的卡多·反腐先锋
These were fully 3D shows that managed to be enjoyable.
这些都是让人感到愉悦的全3D动画
But the problem is I feel these shows were enjoyable in spite of CGs not because of it.
但是我觉得这些动画让我感到愉悦的原因并非CG技术而是CG技术以外的部分
Over the years Polygon Pictures have tried their damned hardest
这些年来
to make a case for fully 3D anime
Polygon Pictures 全力为全3D动画创造市场空间
and continually improves with every project they work on.
并持续改进他们制作的每个项目
But to me it's the same problem.
但对我而言 问题都一样
There's nothing that makes me think
这些都并不足以
I would rather see these shows using CG over traditional animation
让我宁愿看CG动画而不是传统2D动画
if given a expected choice.
如果在可以选择的情况下
That is until we got the one show we were waiting for.
直到我们等到了那个我们一直以来期待的动画
Land of the Lustrous.
宝石之国
A show like this was a long time coming.
这样的一部动画需要很长时间的酝酿
But despite how many opinions it changed about CG anime,
但不管有多少关于CG动画的观点因此而改变
it didn't really do anything new that we have already discussed.
并没有改变我们之前所讨论的内容
What it did do was understand what the strengths were for CG as a tool.
它所做到的是让我们理解使用CG作为工具的优势
and play to those strengths.
并充分利用这些优势
The CG crystal effects of metallic textures
金属纹理带来的水晶CG效果
gave the show a unique visual identity
给动画带来了独特的视觉特征
that wouldn't be a striking if in 2D.
如果在2D情况下就不会有如此冲击力
And the number of dynamic shots it was able to pull off in his action scenes chases
而成功运用动态镜头拍摄出的追逐场景
or just using long shots to build this claustrophobic tension
或者使用长镜头来渲染这种幽闭恐惧的紧张氛围
is something that could only achieved using CG.
都是只有使用CG技术才能达到的效果
Hopefully by the end of this,
希望你在看完视频之后
you can get the idea that
你能知道
despite the reputation CG in anime has right now
不论现在CG动画拥有的名誉如何
CG can look good and has looked good for years
这些年来CG动画看起来都挺不错
even if you're not a fan of the aesthetics scene in Polygon Pictures' works
就算你不喜欢Polygon Pictures 那些作品的艺术风格
or Land of the Lustrous
或者你也不喜欢宝石之国
you've probably appreciated it even if you didn't know.
你也会感谢那些你并不知道的CG技术
But that's just it.
不过也就仅此而已
It's a lose-lose situation.
这是一个双输的情况
Because if CG does its job well,
因为如果CG技术运用得炉火纯青
it won't even be noticed
它甚至不会被察觉出来
but if it does fail
但是如果它失败了
吐槽: 这里好像是Gigguk自嘲了
then it's forever doomed to have some shitty anime youtuber cement it into meme history.
就会被彻底毁掉 并被某些辣鸡油管播主加入陈年老梗豪华午餐
Its failures are exposed
它的失败被曝光了
and its successes are ignored
但是成功却无人问津
but it's important to note that whether it's good or bad
不过不管这是好是坏
largely depends on the understanding from the creater
绝大部分都取决于
of the strengths and limitations of working with CG as a tool
创作者是否理解作为工具的CG技术的优势和限制
as it is with every other medium.
正如许多其他媒介中对CG技术的运用一样
CG has become a standard part of anime nowadays
现在CG技术成为了动画制作中的一个标准环节
so if you're not a fan of that
所以如果你讨厌它
then I can suggest that you watch order anime.
那么我建议你看点老动画
Take the 80s for example.
譬如80年代的那些
注: 这段画面来自电影Tron，提到Tron 的往期视频推荐(av19732601): 虚幻勇士107事实第25(05:40处)
Computer effects may have started to become revolutionary in Hollywood.
那时候 好莱坞正掀起了一波电脑特效革命
But anime was still untouched and pure.
但是动画领域依然保留着那份2D的纯真与美好
You know back then
你知道的
they would never ruin their anime by rendering things using ugly PlayStation 1 graphics.
他们绝不会用辣鸡PS1画质来毁灭他们的动画
Because they were too busy rendering things with a fucking Atari 2600.
因为他们正忙着用更辣鸡的雅达利2600的画质
Hey, bro.
嘿 兄dei
Why is your helicopter Bad CG?
为什么你的直升机是差CG
Why is your face Bad CG?
为什么你的脸是差CG
Why is your life Bad CG?
为什么你的绳命也是差CG
试着不要看任何我刚刚提到的动漫中的CG渲染人群
Hey guys, hope you enjoyed the video.
大家好 希望你们看得开心
注: 赞助链接看简介
Thank you very much this month too.
同样也感谢这个月的这些赞助者
and everyone else on my patreon for helping to support me for this month
以及任何其他这个月在patreon上支持我的人
and making this video possible.
没有你们无法做出这期视频
As you can see I've changed my location back again.
正如你所看到的 我又换了地理位置
I am back in America.
我又回美国了
And I will be attending AX in LA in just a few weeks.
几周后会参加洛杉矶漫展
I have a very busy schedule
日程会有些紧张
so if you're going to be attending AX as well
如果你也参加洛杉矶漫展
keep an eye out for that as I'll be posting that soon.
注意我会很快提到这些事
Anyway that's it for me today.
不管怎么说 今天先到这儿
Not too many updates.
更新不是很多
But until then I've been giguk and I will see you all next time.
下次再见